I'm starting to worry a bit about
artificial or more appropriately named
non-nutrive sweeteners. In the past, I
didn't think much of them, especially
since they have some benefits that are
irrefutable, like helping with weight
loss, fat loss across a series of
randomized control trials. However, more
and more data has come out on other
outcomes like blood sugar, insulin
resistance, and now cognitive health
that don't exactly spell out comfort.
What am I talking about? I'm talking
about this study that's made its way to
my eyeballs.
In this new study, the researchers have
looked at a bunch of non-nutritive
sweeteners. I'm gonna abbreviate them as
sweeteners from now on. And here they
are. and tracked the cognitive decline
by a few different metrics over 8 years
of consumption on average. Now, to be
able to tease out if the sweeteners
track with cognitive decline, the
researchers broke up 12,000 people based
on their amount of consumption, a low,
moderate, or high intake. So the idea
here is that if those that consume more
of these sweeteners have greater
cognitive decline than those who consume
less, there's a link between sweeteners
and cognitive decline. So when we look
at the data here, we're looking at the
measure of verbal fluency, a measure of
cognitive ability. And each line
corresponds to the amount of total
sweetener consumption. The solid blue
line is the lowest consumption. The teal
dotted line is moderate and the reddish
line is the mostest.
We'll pretend that's a word. We have
participants age on the horizontal axis
and the amount of cognitive functional
decline on the vertical. Essentially,
the lower the lines go, the worse. Now,
all three lines go down. Not a surprise
considering age is also a factor in
itself. However, confirmed
statistically, the ones who consume the
most sweeteners as a whole have more
rapid decline. The same was true for
some of the other cognitive measures,
but not all. The main point here is that
non-nutritive sweeteners are associated
with faster cognitive decline. But that
isn't the take-home message because
there's some intriguing nuances that I
think are important here. For one, the
link is stronger in people with
compromised metabolic health, like type
2 diabetes. The relationship was much
weaker in people without diabetes. Those
are still some pretty big buckets, but
they offer us a clue that your current
health dictates if these sweeteners are
more or less associated with faster
cognitive decline. I'm not saying that
if you're healthy, there's no worry,
just that there's less potent of a link.
Now, this study is associative, meaning
that we are linking sweeteners to
cognitive decline, but we aren't saying
sweeteners cause cognitive decline.
Or are we? Well, I'll get into that in
just a moment. There's more that I have
to say on this whole study and others
related like getting into the different
types of non-nutritive sweeteners like
aspartame, saccharine, and more. And if
you're interested in the extended
analysis, check out the Physic Insiders.
It's where I keep the extended version
of the video that you're watching, plus
an accompanying article, actionable
takeaways, a private podcast, live
sessions with me and more. Link to join
is in the description. I'll see you over
there if you're so inclined. Okay, back
to the details. Why might it lean
towards being worrisome?
For many reasons, actually. First, you
remember how we went over the low,
moderate, and high consumption of
non-nutritive sweeteners? Well, the low
consumption went up to 37 milligrams.
The moderate went up to 102 milligrams.
And the highest group went up to 850
milligrams. Now, I know that doesn't
actually mean anything to you, but let
me put this into a more visual
perspective for you. Diet drinks like
Diet Coke or Diet Pepsi or whatever you
choose contain varying levels of these
non-nutritive sweeteners from around 80
to 150 millig. So just a single can per
day is enough to put someone in the
moderate to high consumption group. One
drawback of combining the sweeteners
into these ranges is that some of the
sweeteners are consumed at tens or
hundreds of milligrams while others are
less than a single milligram. So it
muddies the comparisons when looking at
the total. Anyway, the point here is
that even modest sweetener consumption
in a daytoday life puts you in the
higher levels according to this
analysis. So you would have this
association with increased cognitive
decline. The second concern that I have
is that while this study is associative,
they did account for many of the factors
that could explain these results by
adjusting for these factors. So the data
that we looked over earlier is
accounting for these factors because the
group that consumed more of these
non-nutritive sweeteners tended to be a
bit more overweight, eat more, and have
slightly higher incidence of diseases
like cardiovascular disease and others.
So clearly that could easily explain the
more rapid cognitive decline. But the
researchers controlled for that, leaving
the sweetener consumption and whatever
else that wasn't accounted for as a
potential reason for this cognitive
decline. This concern ties in nicely
with the third and likely most powerful.
How do these data compare in
intervention studies? Essentially, if I
give you a sweetener because I'm
threatened by your intelligence, do we
see measurable declines in your mental
performance? I sure hope so. that is
something that we can measure. So I did
a bit of digging. So the good news is
that many intervention studies on the
topic indicate no negative effects even
at very high doses. Yet there are still
other studies that indicate worsening of
cognitive performance. Unfortunately
many of the studies are poor quality,
failing to do the correct statistical
comparisons or improper controls or
giving mixed results. Understandably,
this just makes things altogether that
much more confusing. So, to simplify
everything, here's how I would frame it.
We saw that this associative study
indicates a link between more
non-nutritive sweetener consumption and
cognitive decline, especially true for
people with type 2 diabetes. We also
know that there isn't enough
intervention data to really make a
strong case. So, put yourself in one of
these three buckets. Keep in mind that
these are cognition focused. One, you
would avoid all non-nutritive sweeteners
from here on out. I do not think the
data is strong enough to warrant this
reaction. But if you do not want to
emotionally risk it, no one can argue
with that. Number two, you will lessen
your sweetener consumption out of
caution. If you're concerned about
cognitive health and don't use them for
other reasons, so fat loss as an
example, I think this is reasonable,
especially for two particular
sweeteners, xylitol and arythrtol,
because they showed the greatest
association. And although we don't have
any intervention data, it may be a play
it safer than sorry scenario until we
have more data. Or three, you will
consume these sweeteners without
concern. I do not fall in this camp
anymore. I find myself somewhere between
here and option two. I still think that
non-nutritive sweeteners are beneficial
in many instances, but there's a lot yet
unknown about different sweeteners in
the brain, as is evident by the lack of
intervention data right now. In fact,
some of that caution that I mentioned
specifically about arythrtol and xylitol
has been explored in other studies which
I detail right here. I hope this was
helpful and keep in mind that there's a
lot more to be investigated, especially
as not all sweeteners are the same. I'll
catch you in the next one. Bye.